<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://solidproject.org//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://solidproject.org//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-29T21:50:35+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Solid</title><subtitle>Website for solidproject.org</subtitle><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-10-14</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-10-14" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-10-14" /><published>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-10-14"><![CDATA[<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>

<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>07 October 2021</strong> – This month, <a href="https://vimeo.com/626489187">Solid World October</a> was an amazing continuation of September’s theme about versatility in Solid applications. As we enter the fall months, we see a lot of momentum, creativity, and innovation surrounding Solid and its community members. It’s an exciting time to join or be a part of the community. Tim reiterated this when kicking off the event in turn. This reminds us of just how far we’ve come.</p>

<p>The vitality of Solid is thriving and healthy, as we began to hear from our monthly speakers about their contributions. The first to exemplify this was Ruben Verborgh. Who at the time was standing under the Belgium flag. He was at a convention for the <a href="https://www.tijd.be/app/carousel1/tim-berners-lee-de-bedenker-van-het-internet-we-kunnen-het-wereldwijde-web-nog-fiksen/10309722.html">Government of Flanders working on giving every citizen a Solid Pod</a>. Yes, you read that right, every citizen. But during the event, he gave a high-level overview on access control and consent, specifically explaining how we manage explicit information in our Solid Pods.</p>

<p>Next, we heard from Osmar Olivo, the VP of Product at Inrupt. He presented the big news that Inrupt is holding their first <a href="https://workshop.inrupt.com/home">Developer Workshop</a>. It’s focused on giving all new or enthusiast developers the opportunity and support to build using Solid. You also get a chance to win a cash prize. If you feel ready to sign up you can <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/JH20sRdf">fill out the registration form here</a>. In addition to this great announcement, soon, we will hear more about their upcoming 1.2 release, which is in line with Ruben’s talk about consent.</p>

<p>There were many updates from the Solid Team. Kyra Assaad, a team member, gave us a breakdown of all their action items. First was the SolidProject.org refresh. To improve the website experience for those visiting, they invite participants to schedule a time to run through the site with Marrelle. If you want to help, <a href="https://calendly.com/marrelle-bailey/website-research">sign up here</a>. In addition to the website refresh, they’re also cleaning up the Solid GitHub organization by archiving repos. Also, we are starting Implementer feedback sessions, it’s for those implementing Solid compliant server or client technologies. To reach out, contact feedback@solidproject.org. Her final update was that the Notification Panel is going to start meeting on the 2nd and 4th Thursday of every month. Their mission is to extend technical protocols and vocabularies to facilitate notification exchange in Solid. Learn more at github.com/solid/notifications-panel.</p>

<p>Tani Olhanoski was our first featured presenter for this month. Right now, Metaverse and AI content are hot topics of conversation. And Tani and her team see the value in Solid becoming a Metaverse. Solid could be a space like Ready Player One or the novel Snow Crash by Neal Stephenson that is decentralized, interoperable, and experiential. To take a step in this direction, her team has created <a href="https://www.mysilio.com/">Mysilio</a>. It’s a shared Solid infrastructure, hosts pods, and is a no-code front-end builder. Mysilio helps creators to make their own custom social worlds. There’s an opportunity to <a href="https://mailchi.mp/865966fe3848/mysilio-waitlist">sign-up for their waitlist</a>. To reach out for questions or feedback, reach out to hello@mysilio.com.</p>

<p>Next was Enno Meijers from the National Library of the Netherlands. He’s working on a national Solid-based Collection Registration System to incorporate cultural heritage digitally. As we move to a digital space, improving how we assemble cultural artifacts is vital to hold onto history. Next, he explained how the infrastructure can be decentralized and why Solid created a solution for collecting data, Linked Data. We got the opportunity to see a demo of storing and viewing artifacts from images, descriptions/content, and how it links to other historical pieces. Lastly, he displayed the architecture of the registration system created with the help of <a href="https://www.digita.ai/">Digita</a>. You can view their <a href="https://github.com/netwerk-digitaal-erfgoed/solid-crs">documentation here</a> and watch their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XJgl8EcQqf8">introduction to the Solid CRS app</a>.</p>

<p>Our final presenter was Maria Dimou and Jan Schill <a href="https://indico.cern.ch/event/1082763/attachments/2320087/3950884/SolidWorld2021-10-07presentation.pdf">presenting their PoC</a> <a href="http://getindico.io/">Indico</a>. Indico is an events application that stores comments and gathers information for registration from people’s Solid Pods. It’s an open-source event organization archival and collaboration with CERN, using it for over 850k events. She explained screenshots of how the flow of both registration and comments work. There are a few challenges Jan and Maria are working out to improve the user experience and get support from the CERN team. But in the short term, they have plans for their next steps.</p>

<p>Hearing from all the presenters today proves that there is so much collaboration and contributions happening in Solid. Your work in Solid matters, and if you ever want to showcase your application or work, fill out the <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">Solid World Presenter form today</a>. Make sure you <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/188624118817">sign up for our last Solid World for the year, Solid World November</a>. As we move into the holiday season, we want to give the community and our organizers time to rest and enjoy their families and friends. Our organizing team will use the rest to prepare for our annual kick-off for January 2022. So continue to build, contribute, and share on Solid. We’ll see you next month.</p>

<h3 id="in-other-news">In Other News</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Solid Networking Event – Every last Friday of the month.</li>
  <li>Jackson Morgan will be hosting hosting a kickoff party for <a href="https://www.interesting.chat/">Interesting Chat</a> on 8/18 at 9am PDT, 12pm EDT, and 6pm CEST and streaming it on <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/otherotherjackson">Twtich</a></li>
  <li>Inrupt’s Developer Workshop: https://workshop.inrupt.com/home</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Updates]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-09-09</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-09-09" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-09-09" /><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-09-09"><![CDATA[<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>

<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>02 September 2021</strong> — As we close out the summer for many, we kick off the upcoming fall months with September’s Solid World.  Solid members are making some of the most exciting and unique applications using Solid. This month we dived into learning all the contributions two developers are making with their applications.</p>

<p>Ruben Verborgh started the event by updating everyone about how Solid community members adopt the Community Solid Server. Great news: community members support the new server by sharing what they are working on and possible use cases they see. In addition to this, community members are even making new functionalities. For example, one of the community members created a way to generate modules, <a href="https://github.com/FUUbi/solid-css-demo-module">here’s the demo of how to do that</a>. If you want to find a way to contribute, join the Community Solid Server <a href="https://gitter.im/solid/community-server">gitter channel</a>, share, create, or learn what others are doing.</p>

<p>Next, we had Oz Olivo, who gave a rundown on the Enterprise Solid Sever and Inrupt’s roadmap. For many of us, we are preparing to fill up the coming months with exciting work. Inrupt is no exclusion to this as they plan to get Solid to the forefront of mainstream initiatives. Hopefully, the projects driving this can share their development in a future Solid World. It’s a way for others outside of the community to see what we all see, the promise of Solid. Addedly they are working on getting their V1.2 release out of the door. The beta version will be available for testing next month, including their libraries. So be on the lookout for how you can assist in their beta.</p>

<p>We added a new section to the regular lineup, Solid Team updates. This month we heard from Justin Bingham on what the team is up to. Currently, they are performing user research for the SolidProject.org website. The goal is to adjust the site to be easily consumed and give newcomers and Solid community members the right resources to get involved and make a voice for themselves in the community. In parallel to this effort, the team plans on transitioning the existing Solid Project site to the Community Solid Server. If you would like to volunteer or share your thoughts about the website during the user testing phase, please email the team at info@solidproject.org.</p>

<p>To open up our two featured presenters for this Solid World was Jackson Morgan, who took us to a post-apocalyptic realm. After an alien invasion, who wouldn’t want to connect or meet new people using the <a href="https://www.interesting.chat/">Interesting.Chat app</a>? It’s filled with different interesting and unique topics. It’s all about connecting you with someone else, someone new that is ready to have a conversation with you about anything. It was exciting to see this application working live and hearing Jackson and a new friend converse quickly about Solid. This experience was rewarding to see. Due to the pandemic, we’ve struggled to create human interactions over the last (almost) two years. Here’s a new way for people to talk and make connections about anything using Solid. Want to see the ins and outs of this application? <a href="https://vimeo.com/596683888">Watch the recording of Solid World</a>.</p>

<p>Our final speaker was Frank Smutniak, who showed us how Solid could help you create a healthy garden. With the help of different materials and using Solid Pods, we learned that you could measure moisture levels, report additional measurements and the pump’s status. All of this helps you to adjust how you plant and care for your garden. One of his next steps includes installing and hosting the application on the Community Solid Server. In the coming weeks, he plans to input the information from the presentation to a <a href="https://github.com/itgrows/iot_garden.git">Github repo</a>, so keep an eye out for that.</p>

<p>It’s amazing all that’s capable with Solid, especially when building applications. After hearing about these two unique apps and the positive feedback next month, we decided to spin off the theme to include additional apps that are using Solid. Our next Solid World will be on October 7th! To continue this conversation, join us on the <a href="https://forum.solidproject.org/">Solid Forum</a> or the <a href="https://gitter.im/solid/SolidWorld">Solid World Gitter</a>. Want to participate in these conversations and present at a future Solid World? Fill out the <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">Solid World speaker form</a>. Lastly, the Solid Team can address any questions, comments, or concerns at info@solidproject.org. We hope to see you next month!</p>

<h3 id="in-other-news">In Other News</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Solid Networking Event – Every last Friday of the month. The upcoming gathering is on September 25, 2021 at 11 AM Eastern Time</li>
  <li>David Schmudde created a Node Solid Server notebook in Nextjournal. With a single click a person can remix the notebook and quickly get a Solid server up and running. It also includes thorough documentation on every step and provides an overview of the ideas behind Solid.
If you’d like to consider it for your mailer, the notebook can be found here: https://nextjournal.com/schmudde/node-solid-server.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Vincent Tunru who is a benefit to the community for staying involved!</li>
  <li>AJamesPhillips (username) who is very engaged in the community</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="opportunities">Opportunities</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Recruitment Available: We are strengthening our team - https://www.instans.net - we are bidding for a contract with the Scottish Government to build a MVP for a carbon emissions tracking app, for companies to manage CO2 emissions in their supply chain.<br />
We would like to know who is out there, and who might be interested in participating with us in a 4 month accelerator Oct 2021 to Jan 2022. Ideally, a full stack developer experienced with Node.js, Solid, handling login and authentication. Experience (or interest in learning) search and query would be beneficial.<br />
We are an equal opportunities employer and value diversity. contact@instans.net</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Updates]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-08-12</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-08-12" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-08-12" /><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-08-12"><![CDATA[<h3 id="solid-world">Solid World</h3>
<p><strong>05 August 2021</strong></p>

<p>If there were words to describe August’s Solid World, they were – growth, collaboration, and progress. It was time to look back at all the work we’ve done since the beginning of the year. It’s safe to say we made a lot of progress! Different <a href="https://vimeo.com/585006498">community members gave us updates</a> of their goals and the work they’ve completed so far.</p>

<h4 id="updates">Updates</h4>

<p>Before the presentations kicked off, we got updates from Ruben Verborgh and Oz Olivo. Ruben had exceptional news to tell us. After a year of hard work, he has released <a href="solidproject.org/self-hosting/css">Community Solid Server (CSS) 1.0</a>!  If you’re a developer looking for a companion server to help build your app, or a  researcher exploring the frontier of Solid, try building on CSS.</p>

<p>As the CSS progresses, Oz reminded us that Inrupt’s Enterprise Solid Server is also on track, with the next major release slated for this fall. Also, Inrupt recently composed the <a href="https://www.research.net/r/solidappcompatibility">Solid Application Compatibility Survey</a>, and they are looking to hear feedback from any app developers. With that said, we luckily got to listen to assessments from our presenters.</p>

<h4 id="presentations">Presentations</h4>

<h5 id="solidproject-updates-justin-bingham">SolidProject Updates: Justin Bingham</h5>

<p>Our first presenter was Justin Bingham, the CTO at Janeiro Digital and Solid Team Member. Over the last few months, the Solid Team assigned one of the team members as the project manager to help with the different projects and initiatives. Since the change, Justin leads us through the various tasks they were able to complete. First was migrating the Community Forum to Discourse.org. The second was changing the process of the Solid Application Listing by making it a more collaborative review and submission <a href="https://forum.solidproject.org/c/applications/41">by having it on the Forum</a>. Their latest work is on making substantial updates to the <a href="solidproject.org">solidproject.org website</a>. We all will be excited to see how the changes go!</p>

<h5 id="solid-dei-updates-jeff-zucker">Solid DEI Updates: Jeff Zucker</h5>

<p>Next up, Jeff Zucker, one of the creators for the Solid Team and co-chair of the Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI) Team. During his presentation he explained how the web was created to be a welcoming and inclusive space, and how we’ve moved away from that. With Solid, we can bring diversity, inclusion, and equity back to the web. To help pave the way, a group of Solid members created the DEI Team to help advocate for underrepresented groups. If you would like to join, you can reach out to the <a href="https://gitter.im/solid/DEIT">DEI Team’s Gitter</a>. If you want to watch the DEI Team meetings, you <a href="https://vimeo.com/showcase/8555133">can watch them here</a>.</p>

<h5 id="solid-community-survey-kyra-assaad">Solid Community Survey: Kyra Assaad</h5>

<p>In the same breath of diversity and community, next, we heard about the <a href="https://www.canva.com/design/DAEl-z5tMek/Q8DgVH52TN5Fu90tOBxn9w/view">Solid Community Survey</a>. Kyra Assaad, a Solid team member, co-chair for the DEI Team, and Product Designer at Inrupt, presented the stats from the survey.  Before going into the numbers, she expressed how the DEI and Solid Teams wanted to learn about who’s here and better ways to understand how we can foster the community. And there was so much to learn. We got to know where our community members live, how they identify, their level of knowledge (from code to general education), and ways we can encourage engagement in Solid. She also shared some of the kind words community members think about Solid, like, “Solid is a precondition to the world I want me and my kids to live in.” To help that, the DEI Team’s goal is to take the information from the survey, brainstorm initiatives, and make recommendations for the community and to the Solid Team.</p>

<h5 id="w3c-solid-community-group-sarven-capadisli">W3C Solid Community Group: Sarven Capadisli</h5>

<p>Last but not least, we heard updates from Sarven Capadisli on the W3C Solid Community Group (W3C CG) status update. He mentioned how the work in the specifications, panels, and protocols aligns for society’s betterment and those using Solid for everyday use. If you want to see how each one is doing, check out the Solid Events pages to <a href="https://solidproject.org/events">go over Sarven’s notes</a>.</p>

<h4 id="get-involved">Get Involved</h4>

<p>After hearing from all the presenters, it was great to see the collaborative nature they all had with one another. We are heading in the right direction. As we continue to progress and meet our goals, it’s great to inform the community to see how we surpass expectations. To make this happen, we invite you to join us in the pursuit. To continue this conversation, join us on the <a href="https://forum.solidproject.org/">Solid Forum</a> or the <a href="https://gitter.im/solid/SolidWorld">Solid World Gitter</a>. Want to participate in these conversations and present at a future Solid World? Fill out the <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">Solid World speaker form</a>. Lastly, the Solid Team can address any questions, comments, or concerns at info@solidproject.org. See you next month, September 2nd!</p>

<h4 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Kyra Assaad – For her work on the Community Survey and her presentation of the data during Solid World.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Solid World 05 August 2021]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Started</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//developers/tutorials/getting-started" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Started" /><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//developers/tutorials/00_getting-started</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//developers/tutorials/getting-started"><![CDATA[<h1 id="getting-started-as-a-solid-developer">Getting started as a Solid developer</h1>

<p>To get started with Solid,
you will need a <strong>Solid Pod</strong> and a <strong>WebID</strong>. You can either use an existing Pod provider or run your own server.</p>

<h2 id="existing-provider">Using an existing Pod provider</h2>

<p>You can create a Solid Pod with an existing provider.
For a list of existing Pod providers, see <a href="/users/get-a-pod#get-a-pod-from-a-pod-provider">Solid Pod providers</a>.</p>

<h2 id="own-server">Running your own server</h2>

<p>The following <strong>open-source servers</strong> are available, if you want to run your own:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/CommunitySolidServer/CommunitySolidServer/">Community Solid Server</a> for Node.js</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/solid/node-solid-server">Node Solid Server</a> for Node.js</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/pdsinterop/solid-nextcloud">solid-nextcloud</a> as a plugin for Nextcloud</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/pdsinterop/php-solid-server">PHP Solid Server</a> for PHP</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/manomayam/manas">Manas</a> for Rust</li>
</ul>

<p>For instructions on:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Running the Community Solid Server, see <a href="https://github.com/CommunitySolidServer/CommunitySolidServer#readme">Community Solid Server Readme.md</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Running the Node Solid Server, see <a href="https://github.com/nodeSolidServer/node-solid-server/blob/main/README.md">Node Solid Server Readme.md</a>.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="developing-your-first-app">Developing your first app</h2>

<p>Once you are set up with your own Pod and WebID,
you’re ready to develop your own app. Various Solid client libraries may provide a tutorial for beginners; for example, Inrupt offers the <a href="https://docs.inrupt.com/developer-tools/javascript/client-libraries/tutorial/getting-started/">JS Client Library tutorial</a>, and O.Team offers the <a href="https://github.com/o-development/ldo/blob/main/documentation/solid-react-tutorial.md">Solid-React-LDO tutorial</a>.</p>

<h2 id="community-assistance">Community assistance</h2>

<p>Check out some of the existing applications. Some interesting approaches follow:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>PodOS</strong> (Web Components) https://github.com/pod-os/PodOS</li>
  <li><strong>solid-uix</strong> (Native Web Components) https://github.com/SolidOS/solid-uix</li>
</ul>

<p>Solid with web frameworks:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>ember-solid</strong> — <a href="https://nextcloud.hellofuture.be/s/nYYNwGceFSNotJY">Video Tutorial</a> which should be start-to-finish Solid Ember App (Aad Versteden)</li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://github.com/megoth/todo-ldo">todo-ldo</a></strong> — a [solid/nextjs/ts] app (Arne Hassel)</li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://virginiabalseiro.com/blog/solid-react-app-tutorial">solid-react-app-tutorial</a></strong></li>
</ul>

<p>You can also look into the Solid apps at:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://solidproject.org/apps">Solid Apps</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Youtube videos:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CqI15zs1NHw">How we’re doing Solid — in fewer than 5 minutes</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Tutorials" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Getting started as a Solid developer]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-07-08</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-07-08" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-07-08" /><published>2021-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-07-08"><![CDATA[<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>

<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>1 July 2021</strong> <strong>— Solid World July —</strong> Academics were at the forefront of July’s Solid World. There were many exciting and collaborative pieces coming together this month — from hearing the winner of a Solid challenge to learning how students are innovating new versions of applications.</p>

<p>We missed Tim Berners-Lee, but we felt his well-wishes during the event. In addition, there’s some great news from Ruben Verborgh about the Community Solid Server. He told us how CSS 1.0 is on the right track for its release, and it’s currently in beta. Oz, the VP of Product at Inrupt, gave us an update that Inrupt’s Enterprise Solid Server will be releasing its next version later this year.</p>

<p>Our first presenter was Tonda Karola, a student at the Czech Technical University in Prague. He found Solid on his own and built an <a href="https://github.com/WhyINeedToFillUsername/inbox">email-like application, Inbox</a>. He walked us through the functionality of how his application works. Some of the unique features include Linked Data Notification as communication protocol and ActivityStreams as the format. It runs in a browser with no backend or database, which keeps the data between the user and their Solid pod. His next steps are pagination, more caching, and keeping saved messages.</p>

<p>Next was Dan Barclay, an intern at Inrupt, who gave us a demo of his messaging application called Cend. Cend is easy to use with features like creating different rooms, joining a room with its specific room id number, and making the room public or private. He broke down how the messaging service would work and what he used like solid-client-js, solid-UI-react, and Next JS. It is still in an experimental phase, but you can still <a href="cend-inrupt.vercel.app">try out the application</a>.</p>

<p>Last but not least, Jose Labra, a professor from the University of Oviedo, and Marina Vidiago from Empathy (their partner for the challenge) presented their annual Solid challenge. This is their third year holding the challenge. Each challenge is about having students learn about Solid entirely on their own and creating a theme-specific application with features. This year’s theme was making a friend finder application. The students delivered 18 projects for the course, and three teams decided to participate in Solid Challenge, adding a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FcsDOgOPnX8">promotional video</a>. During the event, we announced the winning team was <a href="https://github.com/Arquisoft/radarin_en3b">Radarin_en3b</a>. One of the team members, Marcos Tobias Muñiz, spoke on behalf of the group, saying very kind remarks. Congratulations to the team!</p>

<p>We continuously learn how Solid is designed to support creators of all backgrounds to build. Exciting times are among us as new and different individuals begin using their skills on Solid. Join us next month to reflect on how this year is going and where we see it moving toward.</p>

<h4 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h4>

<ul>
  <li>David aka Smag0 aka scenaristeur – For his work on trying to figure out what he can do with Solid as an app developer, and learning openly.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Updates]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-06-10</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-06-10" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-06-10" /><published>2021-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-06-10"><![CDATA[<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>3 June 2021</strong> – Solid World June – Another <a href="https://vimeo.com/558597018">Solid World</a> in the books! We explored how Solid refashions data to be human-centric with the intersection of ideas like verifiable credentials, privacy-by-design, data reuse, and consent.</p>

<p>Solid World June kicked off with Tim Berners-Lee giving us updates about the last few weeks. One of the highlights was <a href="https://www.tijd.be/app/carousel1/tim-berners-lee-de-bedenker-van-het-internet-we-kunnen-het-wereldwijde-web-nog-fiksen/10309722.html">his in-person visit to the Flemish Government</a>. Right now, the Flanders Government aims to give everyone in Flanders a Solid Pod. The people of Flanders (and those who follow the Solid community) feel a sense of excitement from seeing all the possibilities that Solid has to offer and the promise of seeing each other in person. He expressed his hopes that others in the community soon get the opportunity to collaborate and feel the vibrancy of our community in person.</p>

<p>Next, we heard from Ruben Verborgh who talked about verifiable credentials (VC). He broke this down for us by explaining how VC, as a W3C standard, could be used to provide consent for data reuse via a consent receipt in Solid Pods.</p>

<p>Oz Olivo, the VP of Product at Inrupt, was the final Solid roadmap update. He discussed the next steps Inrupt is planning for their version 1.2 release and some of the features fell in line with the theme of this month.</p>

<p>Our first presenter, Eliott Behar, focused on how privacy, Solid, and law converge better. He explained how Solid not only meets the standards of General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) but exceeds them. Eliott went over the six lawful bases that the GDPR describes. The final three bases: data retention, data subject rights, and third-party processors, will thrive in Solid. The challenge is what will be the design for it to work in real-life scenarios effectively?</p>

<p>Tom Haegemans from <a href="https://www.digita.ai/">Digita</a> presented data sharing, reuse patterns, and conclusive findings of best practices while operating on Solid. Tom gave the use case of banks and governments who can potentially reuse and move data around. It’s important to realize different parts of our life coincide, like healthcare, banking, and legal documents. When using Solid, we see a new way of accessing this data by having continuous access to different parties. <a href="digita.ai/resources">Digita looked at the forming patterns</a> revealed when discovering how to reuse the data and who’s involved in each user’s journey. In the end, we saw that there’s a pattern framework we can use when thinking about legal considerations.</p>

<p>Last but not least, Greg Golding and Anton Wiklund, from the <a href="https://www.digg.se/om-oss/nyheter/2021/vardefullt-for-individen-att-fa-okad-insyn-och-kontroll-over-sin-data">Swedish Public Employment Service</a> showed us how consent could work using Solid. Their <a href="https://gitlab.com/arbetsformedlingen/individdata/rupoc">Proof of Concept (PoC)</a> was about a job seeker granting and revoking access to their application to a prospective employer. The work happening around compliance, consent, data reuse, privacy, and law shows promise for the web being a place where individuals have true control over their data and information.</p>

<p>Each month we dive into new and valuable conversations about how Solid is bettering not only the web, but your world. As our world and community begin to reopen, we see our lives differently. Technology and data will never be the same, and Solid is changing it for the better. To continue this conversation, join us on the <a href="https://forum.solidproject.org/">Solid Forum</a>. Want to participate in these conversations and present at a future Solid World? Fill out the <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">Solid World speaker form</a>. Lastly, the Solid Team can address any questions, comments, or concerns at info@solidproject.org.</p>

<h3 id="solid-community-survey">Solid Community Survey</h3>
<p>The first ever Solid Community Survey is live! The survey is designed to learn about the makeup of the community and discover ways to strengthen the community. Make sure to participate to have your voice heard.</p>

<p><strong>Survey Link</strong>
https://research.typeform.com/to/e9dsorQz</p>

<p>The survey will be open until <strong>Friday, June 25, 4:00pm Eastern Time</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="in-other-news">In Other News</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/understory-digital-garden-club-tickets-151311208899">Digital Garden Club Event</a> – Monthly Basis</li>
  <li>Solid Networking Event – June 25, 2021 at 10 AM Eastern Time</li>
  <li><a href="https://vimeo.com/561179521">Diversity, Equity, &amp; Inclusion Meeting</a> July 8, 2021 at 11 AM ET/ 5 PM CEST</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h4>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Alain Bourgeois, for his continued efforts in maintaining the codebase of Node Solid Server, helping develop the Solid Operating System, SolidOS — also keeping the solidcommunity.net server running and up to date.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Marrelle Bailey for her work in the community — like helping us set up a Diversity, Equity and Inclusion team. And stepping up to help our community be more engaged and encouraged overall.</p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Events]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-05-06</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-05-06" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-05-06" /><published>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-05-06"><![CDATA[<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>6 May 2021</strong> – This month during <a href="https://vimeo.com/546202189">Solid World</a>, we got to see links between different implementations and applications built using Solid. Each month our community not only grows in size but in solidarity. We heard from three presenters about advanced application features and the server technology that makes them possible.</p>

<p>We kicked off this month’s event with Tim Berners-Lee. He expressed excitement about building an ecosystem that creates opportunities for UX/UI designers, application testers, and others to join our community. He also asked for volunteers to work on the Solid Operating System (OS), if individuals had time. If you are interested, you can visit the <a href="https://github.com/solid/solidos">Github repository</a> or send a message to the <a href="https://gitter.im/solid/solidos">Solid OS Gitter channel</a>.</p>

<p>Next, we got an update from Ruben Verborgh for the Community Solid Server (CSS). He mentioned a hot topic in the community right now, verifiable credentials (VC). Putting down the framework for VC, Ruben went into more detail about how it’s the perfect match to Solid.</p>

<p>After the roadmap updates were the presentations. First, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jacksoncmorgan/">Jackson Morgan</a> from <a href="https://o.team/">OTeam</a> gave a festive presentation about his new chat application, Liqid Chat. During the event, Jackson opened the app for a hands-on demo by allowing the Solid World attendees to <a href="https://tinyurl.com/liqid-chat">chat during the presentation</a>. By the end of the event,  full conversation and gifs were shared without any issues throughout his presentation. In addition, Jackson shared two repos to check out the back end of the application, <a href="https://github.com/o-development/ochat-client">one for the client</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/o-development/ochat-api">other on the API</a>.</p>

<p>Next, Christian Buggedei presented <a href="https://darcy.is/">Darcy’s</a> two prototypes, the former IBEX and the newest Shepherd. The latest version of the social application helps to onboard those new to the Solid community or ecosystem. It helps from creating a WebID (or account) on Solid to setting up a private feed. Even though they have built a stable application, they are looking for help. Thinking about helping? <a href="https://opencollective.com/darcy-is/updates/we-are-looking-for-help">Click here</a> to get involved with their work.</p>

<p>Lastly, we heard from Aaron Coburn and Jack Lawson from Inrupt, who gave us an update about a Solid feature that helps applications like Jackson’s and Christian’s projects update their users in real-time. This new feature, Notifications, was recently released as part of the version 1.1 launch. We also got to see a <a href="https://notifications-demo.docs.inrupt.com/">demo of just how the notifications function</a> and how fast they are.</p>

<p>We are starting to see how all our work intersects with others and we are noticing just how excited those in the community are about it all. Remember that if you would like to present at a future Solid World, fill out the <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">Solid World speaker form</a>. Lastly, the Solid Team can address any questions, comments, or concerns at info@solidproject.org.</p>

<h3 id="in-other-news">In Other News</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Solid Networking Event – May 28, 2021 at 10 AM Eastern Time</li>
  <li>Lotico’s Event <a href="http://www.lotico.com/index.php/Your_Personal_Linked_Data_Graphs_with_Solid">Your Personal Linked Data Graphs with Solid</a> – May 27, 2021</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/understory-digital-garden-club-tickets-151311208899">Digital Garden Club Event</a> – Monthly Basis</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jacksoncmorgan/">Jackson Morgan</a> for his recent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCMVpUX6URfy5SnRn9OWteyQ">explainer videos</a>!</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Events]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-04-08</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-04-08" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-04-08" /><published>2021-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-04-08"><![CDATA[<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>

<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>1 April 2021</strong> — 
It’s always fantastic to hear how contributors are improving Solid, its ecosystem, and the community. During <a href="https://vimeo.com/531907097">Solid World April</a>, we heard from a few server developers about their work with Solid. Before hearing from our presenters, we kicked off the event, getting a high-level overview from Tim Berners-Lee.</p>

<p>Tim commemorated the <a href="https://webfoundation.org/2021/03/web-birthday-32/">Web’s 32nd birthday</a> by reflecting on building a better web. He emphasized that Solid is at the forefront of improving the web. Lastly, he shouted out three Community Spotlights, Angelo Veltens, Alain Bourgeois, and Sharon Stratsianis, for their contributions to the Solid community.</p>

<p>Next, we heard a quick update and demo from Ruben Vergborgh regarding the Community Solid Server (CSS). Continuous updates on the CSS are building toward the V1.0 release.</p>

<p>Osmar (Oz) Olivo, the VP of Product at Inrupt, gave Solid World attendees a preview of some release news that will be coming later this month, focused on security. He also mentioned the Swedish Government’s work with Solid, and encouraged users of Inrupt’s products, to fill out  their <a href="https://www.research.net/r/GWWJB7V">product survey</a>.</p>

<p>Our first guest presenter was <a href="https://graphmetrix.com">Graph Metrix</a>. Kai Gilb and Frederick Gilbert presented their work on Solid. It focused on building a conceptual AI, an ontology, and support of a one-world data model. With these three concepts in mind, they showcased TrinPod, where all your information can live. We saw just how in-depth their work could be with a flow chart and the layers of files, folders, and other information that one person can have. Their targeted use cases center around construction, productivity applications, logistics, and property. It showed versatility and a solution for real-world pain points by leveraging Solid. If you would like to create your own TrinPod, you can <a href="https://trinpod.us/">sign up for a free account</a> and start using their suite of applications.</p>

<p>Following Graphmetrix was the <a href="https://pdsinterop.org">PDS Interop</a> group (made up of four developers) working with <a href="https://nextcloud.com/">Nextcloud</a>. <a href="https://github.com/ylebre">Yvo Brevoort</a> talked about their journey on Solid by building a <a href="https://github.com/solid/test-suite">Solid Test Suite</a>. It helped them learn about the ecosystem and build a foundation for different servers to be interoperable. They also have two server-related projects, the <a href="https://github.com/pdsinterop/php-solid-server">PHP Solid Server</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/pdsinterop/solid-nextcloud">Nextcloud Solid Server</a>. They are moving into the next steps in their venture and are looking for help. With that said, if you’re interested, reach out to <a href="https://github.com/ylebre">Yvo Brevoort</a>.</p>

<p>Our final presenter was Antonio Rodríguez Santiesteban from <a href="https://spoter.me">Spoter.ME</a>. He explained how they are building a Solid Pod Provider that is scalable, resilient and has open microservices architecture. The demo showcased how to access your Pod and add files and other information to it. With the Pod provider up and running, they invite users, application developers, and application providers to test it out; if you would like to, reach out to them at <a href="mailto:info@spoter.me">info@spoter.me</a>.</p>

<p>Solid World brought great presenters and showcased how different Solid services are. From seeing interoperability between servers, test-users are getting their foot in the door. If you would like to present at a future Solid World, fill out the <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">Solid World speaker form</a>. Lastly, the Solid Team can address any questions, comments, or concerns at info@solidproject.org.</p>

<h3 id="in-other-news">In Other News</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Solid Networking Event – Friday, April 30, 2021 at 10 AM Eastern Time</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Sharon Stratsianis for her work on SolidOS.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Updates]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-03-11</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-03-11" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-03-11" /><published>2021-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-03-11"><![CDATA[<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>

<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>04 March 2021</strong> — It was exciting to see the great turnout at March’s Solid World. We continue to grow in the Solid community as reflected in Solid World’s highest attendance ever. During the event, we got to touch on a lot of great ideas related to the growing market of interoperability.</p>

<p>Tim Berners-Lee kicked off the event with shout-outs to last month’s Community Spotlights: <a href="https://www.virginiabalseiro.com/">Virginia Balseiro</a> for building <a href="https://www.womenofsolid.org/">Women of Solid</a> and <a href="https://www.digita.ai/">Digita</a> for their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCA22hu-0VEHt5tCc7jad74g">introduction videos</a> as well as their contributions in discovering and reporting bugs.</p>

<p>Next, Ruben Verborgh gave updates and a demo of the Community Solid Server (CSS). Recently, CSS’s version 0.8 was released with 1.0 on the horizon. He also created a <a href="https://css.verborgh.org/public/2021/Solid%20World/Chat/">chat from his pod</a>, where attendees were able to engage with during the event.</p>

<p>For Inrupt’s update, Osmar Olivo, VP of Product, gave us a sneak peek that  Enterprise Solid Server (ESS) version 1.1 will be released in early spring. He also reminded us to try out and <a href="https://inrupt.atlassian.net/servicedesk/customer/portal/7">give feedback</a> for <a href="https://signup.pod.inrupt.com/">Pod Spaces</a>.</p>

<p>Next were our two guest presenters for Solid World. We heard from Dmitri Zagidulin and Liam Broza from <a href="https://lifescope.io/">LifeScope</a>, who let us know about their work with Solid. They are working on creating a “companion intelligence” by using Artificial Intelligence (AI) to create a digital memory of yourself, one that builds up a more accurate, personalized, and improved experience on the web. They will be using Solid to help with decentralizing their data storage and authorization. You can access their slides <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1vg9y_o0KtaC1j9w6yxpukEeoOsdbMCQa2zh1hQO2pYw">here</a>.</p>

<p>Last but not least, we heard from Dick van Gelder from Creafree. He discussed the importance of us coming together as a collective to support and protect intellectual property. Working with existing laws, we can use Solid to build a space for people to create and share their creations. The ability to gather and use all your data with different applications is just a start. You can access his slides <a href="https://ln2.sync.com/dl/53b6274d0/fcs466su-bs8bgykx-hkfmpz2a-rmwamczt/view/default/9895814900003">here</a>.</p>

<p>We continue to build steps to give individuals, organizations, and developers the ability to use data in a new, innovative, and valuable way. Solid is always growing in size and contributions. As we continue through this year, it will be exciting to see how we can grow in interoperability and integrations together!</p>

<h3 id="in-other-news">In Other News</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://jackson.solidcommunity.net/public/solid-networking/03-2021.html">Solid Networking Event</a> – March 26, 2021 at 10 AM Eastern Time</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h4>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Angelo Veltens – For his work testing the chat apps that were posted on the forum recently, and working with the developers to help them pinpoint issues he encountered. Also got back to someone who did not manage to get Solid working in a browser extension a while ago, sharing how he now did manage to do that.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Alain Bourgeois – He’s done a great job of keeping NSS up to date as well as supporting a few applications.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Want something mentioned? Contact the Solid team at info@solidproject.org. If you would like to speak at Solid World please fill <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">this form out</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Updates]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Month in Solid 2021-02-04</title><link href="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-02-04" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Month in Solid 2021-02-04" /><published>2021-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://solidproject.org//newsletter/this-month-in-solid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://solidproject.org//newsletter/2021-02-04"><![CDATA[<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>

<h3 id="events"><a href="https://solidproject.org/events">Events</a></h3>

<p><strong>4 February 2021</strong> - Here’s the update from Solid World. We started the month off by hearing the ins and outs of applications using Solid as their backend. Last Thursday, we got to learn from presenters how to use applications in different facets.</p>

<p>We got to understand the excitement that this brings to our community by Tim Berners-Lee. The community is growing. New individuals are building a way for themselves, and we see their creations developing into some great applications. As we continue to grow, we need to keep up the momentum by supporting our builders and our community members. We saw a significant increase in activity this month due to recent press attention. Tim was recently featured in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/10/technology/tim-berners-lee-privacy-internet.html?smid=tw-share">New York Times</a> and spoke at the <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-tech-bernerslee-interview/father-of-the-web-tim-berners-lee-prepares-do-over-idUSKBN29H1JK">Reuters Next conference</a>. Like we said in <a href="https://vimeo.com/498076263">January’s Solid World</a>, our foundation is there. Now it’s time to develop.</p>

<p>Ruben Verborgh shared a helpful resource he created for the Community Solid Server, its <a href="https://github.com/solid/community-server-recipes">recipes</a> for interoperability. Osmar Olivo, VP of Product for Inrupt, let us know there is now Node.js support for Inrupt’s <a href="https://docs.inrupt.com/developer-tools/javascript/client-libraries/">Solid Client Libraries</a>. If you want to hear or see it in detail, you can watch the recording of Solid World <a href="https://vimeo.com/solidworld/february2021">here</a>.</p>

<p>Three presenters gave us an idea of just what it’s like to create a Solid application. Our first presenter <a href="https://noeldemartin.com/">Noel DeMartin</a> gave us a demo of <a href="https://noeldemartin.github.io/media-kraken/login">Media Kraken</a>. Noel showcased the different ways you can log into and store the media/entertainment data in the application and on your computer. One of the significant aspects of the presentation was when Noel opened the door for other applications to interoperate with Media Kraken. One thing that makes Solid unique is creating interoperability between all servers, clients, and applications. Noel’s presentation reminds us of how possible it is. He is also a great point of reference when starting. If you’re new, check out his <a href="https://noeldemartin.com/tasks/">journal</a>.</p>

<p>Next, Jasmine Leonard presented <a href="https://podexplorer.gigalixirapp.com">PodExplorer</a>. Jasmine is new to the Solid community, joining in late 2020. While learning how to get engaged with Solid she built her application. When using the app, you can access data from your pod, upload, delete and view various files. During the presentation, Jasmine shared a few resources that helped build the PodExplorer—mentioning places like the <a href="https://forum.solidproject.org/">Solid Forum</a>, <a href="http://solidproject.org/">Solid Website</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/solid/solidproject.org">GitHub Repos</a>. In the future, Jasmine expects to add additional functionality to PodExplorer, such as: bulk actions, managing the access of data, and finding files in your pod.</p>

<p>Finally, Hindia Mohammed from <a href="https://ekseli.fi/">Ekseli</a> gave us a business to business (B2B) view of applications. Hindia, the CTO of Ekseli,  presented Projectware. The project management application provides two interfaces: the Delivery and Sales Portals. In addition to presenting Projectware, Hindia shared the ways Ekseli engages in the Solid Community. Contributions in various facets are essential for the Solid ecosystem to thrive.</p>

<p>This Solid World was certainly rewarding to see new, consistent, and supportive Solid community members present at Solid World. It’s important to note that Solid welcomes developers of all levels (beginners to seasoned) and those new to the community. If you would like to learn more about presenting at a future Solid World, please fill out <a href="https://es1cz4pb7oi.typeform.com/to/nietD34f">this form</a>. As we continue to build on Solid, we also need to give new community members the resources and spaces to be active.</p>

<h3 id="press"><a href="https://solidproject.org/press">Press</a></h3>

<h3 id="community-spotlight">Community Spotlight</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.digita.ai/">Digita</a> for their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCA22hu-0VEHt5tCc7jad74g">introduction videos</a> and for finding the <a href="https://inrupt.com/security/advisories/">NSS vulnerability</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.virginiabalseiro.com">Virginia Balseiro</a> created the <a href="https://www.womenofsolid.org/">Women of Solid</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="job-openings">Job Openings</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/view/2365589216/">OECO Group is looking for a full-stack Solid developer in Kontich, Belgium</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Updates" /><category term="monthly" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Updates]]></summary></entry></feed>